Preliminary Guide to the South Coast Railroad Museum Collection
Department of Special Collections
South Coast Railroad Museum Collection
ca. 1878-1976
1950-1968
SBHC Mss 18
South Coast Railroad Museum
ca. 10 linear feet (6 record center containers, 1 oversize box, 2 telescoping boxes).
University of California, Santa Barbara. Library. Dept. of Special Collections Santa Barbara, CA 93106
Mostly printed materials, such as pamphlets, brochures, guides, and timetables, relating to railroad history, with some emphasis on California.
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the South Coast Railroad Museum Board, 1991-1995.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection includes histories, timetables, annual reports, travel brochures, official guides, catalogs, magazines, manuals, equipment registers, maps, blueprints, trip passes, and other ephemera relating to railroad lines primarily in North America. There are a few late 19 and early 20th century items, but the bulk of the collection is from the 1950s-1960s.
The collection contains the following series:
Companies (Boxes 1-4). Arranged alphabetically, by name of the railroad.
Railroad Organizations and Publishers (Boxes 4-6). Arranged alphabetically by name or title of publication.
Oversize
Boxed (Box 7).
Rolled (8-9).
The appended list, with further description of the contents of the collection, was prepared by Gary Coombs, director of the Museum.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
South Coast Railroad Museum; Railroads--North America.
Related Materials
UCSB Special Collections:
Myrick, David. Author of numerous books on railroads in the West.
Romaine Trade Catalog Collection. Catalogs on railroad supplies.
Wyles Collection. Printed materials relating to the role of the railroads in the Civil War and the development of the West, including transcontinental railroads.
Other Institutions:
California State Archives.
California State Railroad Museum.
Minnesota Historical Society. Great Northern Railway materials.
- Companies
  - Alaska Railroad (Box 1)
  - American Locomotive Company (Box 1)
  - American Railway Express Co. (Box 1)
  - Amtrak (Box 1)
  - Arizona Eastern Railroad (Box 1)
  - Atlanta and West Point Railroad (West Point Route) (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Coast Line Railroad (Box 1)
  - Baldwin Locomotive Works (Box 1)
  - Baltimore Annapolis Railroad (Box 1)
  - Baltimore Ohio Railroad (Box 1)
  - Burlington Route (Box 1)
  - Canadian National Railways (Box 1)
  - Canadian Pacific (Box 1)
  - Central of Georgia Railway (Box 1)
  - Central Vermont Railway (Box 1)
  - Chesapeake Ohio Railway (also incl. Baltimore Ohio) (Box 1)
  - Chicago, Burlington and Quincy Railroad (Box 1)
  - Chicago Eastern Illinois Railroad (Box 1)
  - Chicago North-Western Railway (Box 1)
  - Chicago South Shore and South Bend Railroad (Box 1)
  - Chihuahua Al Pacifico (Box 1)
  - Cumbres Toltec Scenic Railroad (Box 1)
  - Denver Rio Grande Western Railroad (Box 1)
  - East Broad Top Railroad (Box 1)
  - Erie Lackawanna Railroad (Box 1)
  - GM (diesel locomotives) (Box 1)
  - Grand Trunk Railroad System (Box 1)
  - Grand Trunk Western - Canadian National Railways (Box 1)
  - Great Northern Railway (Box 1)
  - Green Mountain Railroad (Box 1)
  - Gulf, Mobile Ohio (GMO) (Box 1)
  - Illinois Central System (Box 1)
  - Kansas City Southern Lines (Box 1)
  - Long Island Railroad (Box 1)
  - Louisiana Western Railroad Co. (Box 1)
  - Milwaukee Road (Box 1)
  - Missouri Pacific Lines (Box 1)
  - Mount Washington Cog Railway (New Hampshire) (Box 1)
  - National Railways of Mexico (Box 2)
  - New York Central Railroad (Box 2)
  - Nickel Plate Road (Box 2)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway (Box 2)
  - Northern Alberta Railways (Box 2)
  - Northern Pacific Railway (Box 2)
  - Northwestern Pacific Railroad Company (Box 2)
  - Ontario Northland Railway (Box 2)
  - Pacific Electric Railway (Box 2)
  - Pacific Great Eastern Railway Co. (Box 2)
  - Penn Central (Box 2)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad (Box 2)
  - Pickwick Stages (Box 2)
  - Puget Sound and Snoqualmie Valley Railroad (Box 2)
  - Pullman Co. (Box 2)
  - Reading Railway System (Box 2)
  - Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railway (Box 2)
  - Rock Island (Box 2)
  - San Diego Arizona Eastern (Box 2)
  - Santa Fe (incl. Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway Company) (Box 2-3)
  - Seaboard Air Line Railroad (Box 3)
  - Silverton RR (Box 3)
  - Sonora Baja Railway (Box 3)
  - Soo Line (Box 3)
  - Southern Pacific (Box 3-4)
  - Union Pacific Railroad (Box 4)
  - Union Switch Signal Co. (Box 4)
  - Wabash Railroad Company (Box 4)
  - West River Railroad (Box 4)
  - Western Pacific (incl. California Zephyr) (Box 4)
  - White Pass Yukon Route (Box 4)
  - Worthington (locomotive equipment) (Box 4)
- Railroad Organizations and Publishers
  - Association of American Railroads
    - Bibliography of Railway Literature, 1950 (Box 4)
    - List of Principal Railroads in the United States, with Home Address of Each, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Quiz on Railroads and Railroading, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Standard Code of Operating Rules, Block Signal Rules, Interlocking Rules, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Curran Dinsmore Co - "American Railway Guide and Pocket Companion ..." 1845 (1945 facsimile) (Box 4)
  - Examination on Rules and Regulations of the Transportation Department for Train Dispatchers, Conductors, and Engineers, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Federation for Railway Progress - Railway Progress, 1957 (Box 4)
  - [German Railroads] - vom Adler zum Komet, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Golden West Books - 1967 Railroad Calendar (Box 4)
  - Lionel Rail Road Company - Lionel Accessory Catalog, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Locomotive Photograph Company - catalog and price list, ca. 1953 (Box 4)
  - National Railway Historical Society - calendar, 1975 (Box 4)
  - National Railway Publication Co. - Official Guide of the Railways, 1964-1970 (Box 4-5)
  - Railway Equipment and Publication Co.
    - Official Railway Equipment Register, 1966-1975 (Box 5-6)
    - Official Railway Guide - North American Freight Service Edition, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Official Register of Passenger Train Equipment, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Railroad Magazine, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Rand McNally - Handy Railroad Atlas of the United States, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Traffic Publishing Co. - Freight Traffic Red Book, 1945 (Box 6)
- Oversize
  - Boxed
    - Blueprints (Box 7)
    - Maps (Box 7)
  - Rolled
    - Maps (Box 8-9)